last thing this whole idea of in these
times of great and uncertainty in this
time of such a virus going around these
troubled time such a difficult time no
time to not know what is the practice
now yeah as if it was something
different hmm as it was anything before
so when things are comfortable I don't
practice but when things are it's
difficult that's really gonna front
yeah that's what I get reminded of the
practice yeah so you kind of well it's a
really procrastination no the issue
there it's more like intoxication with
the good times intoxication with the
with the health intoxication with safety
with lack of risk with lack of illnesses
intoxication with with that whole
current state of affairs because of that
you don't really like you don't you
don't make the effort to do what you
know should be done because you kind of
also know that health will not last
forever but while your deaths that's
where the would refer to as intoxicated
you are intoxicated health with youth
with life because you genuinely think
like a drunk person who when he's drunk
he is invincible he knows it's not true
but he doesn't he doesn't feel like it's
not true
it feels like it's true like this this
is this state are great I have to seize
it I will make most of it and because of
that you don't actually you know you
voluntarily lose perspective but you
have a choice you cannot lose
perspective there and you can ask
yourself ok I am healthy now but can
that change yes the answer is immediate
I'm alive now but can that change yes
another immediate answer but that answer
requires maintenance you need to keep
sort of keep keeping up with that
context because it's too easy to ignore
because it's pleasant it's sorry it's
unpleasant to keep looking at it or to
get sick
I could get like you know who Danny
obviously my my youth my strength is
fading I can't measure how much but it has to
I can't measure how much but it has to
but it's easy to not think about it
especially because you don't see any any
drawback in not thinking about it that's
a way that we have to instruct monks and
people to make the effort to start
seeing the drawbacks in these things
which will then keep you in check but
without it
without making that effort you're not
gonna see the drawbacks but then it's
kind of when things are difficult you do
want to practice more well because now
you see a drawback yeah ladies no it's
it's thrown in your face yeah but if
it's too difficult there's no
possibility we're shutting down more
often yeah more often than not its kind
of too late if you wait it until okay
now you're really sick that's it and now
you want to practice yeah that's a bit
you should have left it that fine that's
where the good again will tell monks to
to to basically we draw themself and
live in seclusion and make the effort
less to regret it later on well because
the time will come worried to be it will
be too late for the others and too much
yeah exactly that's I mean it's too late
you can't do anything about it because
it's just too much to bear or simply
your health is gone now and you're just
in constant pain and so on you have to
prepare beforehand in it with wisdom so
well that's what we don't is for seeing
things before they occur you don't know
what you want to practice restraint yeah
but
good restraint not just blind restraint
yeah yeah so you get a bit of a painting
it is painful celibacy's pain exactly
yet that pain that discomfort will keep
you on the edge to keep you well bending
see that pain is is in your own control
that pains me that's the cure Saguna
referred to is known called as a pain of
renunciation and that's up to you you
choose to renounce things on account of
which you experience that pain but if
you start evolving with the Muriel as
pain is not optional there has to be
pain and the only choice you have it's
not like whether you're not gonna have
any pain it's whether it's gonna be on
your own terms or not on your own terms
so you replace the pain of household
life as the Buddha said as in the pain
of sensuality gain loss phase blame all
these worldly wins you would replace
those pains with pains of restraint and
then you see oh when I have pains of
restraint I can't have the pain so far
so life and these pains of restraint are
not actually paints from the point of
view of the pains of household life they
are easy to bear they are not painful
actually I don't have the same amount of
pressure needing to get rid of them
that's if you develop wisdom on account
of restraint initially of course
restraint will be restraint will be
overwhelming it but you it's the only
reason that it's overwhelming is because
the mind is too weak to bear it the mind
still acts out of the assumption that I
must be free from pain at all cost but
that's not optional
for as long as there is this body there
will be pain arising in the same sense
for as long as this body do be pleasure
arise so then again you replace the
pleasure of the household life pleasure
of sensuality eating whenever you want
all these things you replace it with the
pleasure of renunciation with freedom
that comes from it with burden lessness
of it complete lack of pressure like
genuine like lightness like there is
absolutely nothing you do you have to do
you can achieve anything
and the the the sort of worldly benefit
as well of doing that safe eating once a
day mmm and choosing that yeah while you
got plenty of free you could yeah eat
all day if you want sure George you
choose not to so that when there's a
time of famine in when it's difficult to
get food then well you'll be fine but
you don't even need to think like with
some doomsday scenario at the back of
your mind you just want to have an
option I'll either have discomfort on
account of my own well a recent will and
intention and choice all I have a
discomfort on account of my own
unrestrained desire that controls me
which is which pain is better which pain
is less risky which pain is less wild
which pain is less likely to result in
greater unpleasant repercussions in you
saying no in restraining yourself or the
news saying yes and riding that wild
desire for a wherever it takes you
scratching a rich like a maniac which
one do you think it's going to result in
worse states of mind you already know
that everybody knows that so that I mean
it's not overnight you will be celibate
and never eat again but you need to
adopt that as a value that your desires
need to be restrained and your desires
are not rooted in these random things in
beautiful sight sound smell taste
touches they're rooted in your own
intentions that's how you will learn
where the problem is as the Buddha said
man sensuality is not the beautiful
things in the world that you can see
your taste of touch its his thoughts
that's what sensuality is rooted but you
never get to see the roots of that
sensuality if you never restrain your
own actions and your own senses and
that's again exactly another thing you
don't need to wait until it's too late
until your senses start decaying and so
on in order to practice that actually if
you wait then it will be too late
because if you if you did not if you
could not restrain your senses while
they were still relatively young and
operating normally basically while the
domains of those senses were clear to
you sites were clear pleasures for the sites
sites were clear pleasures for the sites
were clear
you're not gonna restrain it when it's
all gone basically you become senile and
you can't see well you can't hear well
everything is uncomfortable
everything is just too much weight on
you so when you had an option to
exercise strength and develop strength
you didn't
now you come nice even the bare minimum
that's required for you to start
developing strength it's too much yeah
because you waited too long the same for
health life anything like you don't want
to wait till it's too long
and if sometimes you get complacent like
because you know something there's
nothing bothering you you're kind of
practicing so you don't feel necessarily
guilty that you're lazy or
procrastinating but you know you are
getting complacent you maybe have
trouble seeing where the problem is well
just maybe turn up your restraint or not
and the pain will come and that's your
work Oh am i resisting this pain am i
fearing this pain now trying to justify
my actions to get rid of this pain
whatever genuinely because this is not a
pain that harms me by the way
say no to smell sight smell taste
touches doesn't harm you at all
literally there is no threat no danger
in saying no to not look at something in
saying no to not taste something that is
really nothing dangerous yet it's the
worst type of pain why is that all
because the mind and the senses are used
to going whatever desire wants to go so
it's like catching a wild dog it will be
kicking and screaming and trying to bite
your face off
if you if you if you tie down first time
because he in his mind it's fighting for
its life but it's actually safe it's
actually yeah this is this yeah that's
the safety buddy doesn't recognize this
search but once he comes down then he
gets to recognize it and then once
completely tame then its team and fix I
mean the Buddha compared your own mind
and senses me exactly always to wild
animals to the big independent bull
elephant they need to catch and and
strap down with the big sort of chains
and leather belts until it basically
until it comes down and then it will
listen to you same you need to restrain
your senses and then eventually they
will listen to you know you to them so
yes sometimes these things like people
can get reminders of Oh
health is a you know a precarious thing
it can quickly change life is precarious
thinking will change
so whatever would inspire you to
practice in the right direction they
have the right type of contemplation
that's fine that's good but you can also
find that inspiration within yourself
and not wait to be prompted externally
because more often than not the external
promise means it's too late like there
there were some cases in the sisters who
had external prompts as a result of that
they made the effort and purify the mind
completely it should be waiting a great
time but I think those cases are far
fewer in number which is why we still
talk about them today two millennia
later like they were so profound
you know the inspirational stories that
that's why I still remember them but far
fewer than the actual the ones they were
not you know they were facing these
adverse circumstances and had no
direction of practice this is a direct
look for foresight hmm that is having a
perspective on exactly having a better
greater perspective but elevate the
ground like you find a way to climb onto
the elevator ground and you see
perspective is is far it's farther
reaching from here then if I come down
so I have an option I'll either come
down and enjoy whatever fruit grows at
the bottom of this hill but I won't see
any danger coming because I've been
toxic alien chasing down
berries and apples or I can perhaps you
know have my expectations in terms of
providing objects for my sense desires
but then stay in the place of safety
from which I can see the danger coming
from far far far beyond and that's all
within like within everyone's mind like
even now yeah I might not see the end of
this day even if nothing happens to your
heart I've stopped as we said that
before in those talks on modern answer
not on a sudden so you realize okay so I
don't know so what do I do what you do
is don't lose perspective then you heart
my stuff at the end of the day and all
you need to do is protect that
perspective everything else will come
out of it
natural non desire will come out of it
non hatred will come out non distraction
will come on peace will come out because
the only reason people don't live in
peace is the because they keep
disturbing themselves by allowing their
own senses to drag them left and right
like imagine you get a big dog on a
leash it's stronger than you and it sees
rabbit or squirrel and you tight it it
will be very painful but if you have
doesn't matter how big the dog is if
it's trained and if it is slightest sort
of tightness of the leash it will stop
see you release you are not threatened
in many people know implicitly that if
circumstances to were to change and they
were to be pushed to the limits due to
circumstances to do sensuality your will
or something happening
they have implicit sort of recognition
of the fear that they will completely
lose control and and it's frightening no
idea where you gonna end up and
sometimes people yet and that where they
don't end up on account of just careless
decisions and choices
and all of that is rooted in not having
that fundamental perspective on your own
situation all of that is rooted in
presently basically enduring
intoxication that's that's the like a
basis of the mind you think you will
live forever you will be healthy forever
and you will be sort of your senses will
be operating properly strongly clearly
forever like you'll be you've never
gonna age now we're gonna go to crack it
and these these little reminders of the
perspective would be much more apparent
and much more self-evident if people
would spend there most of the time
within the renunciation and sensory
strength not within sensuality and
desire you lose perspective as the
Buddha called basically sensuality and
other hindrances that the weakness of
wisdom so as we compare the wisdom to
that elevator grant from which you have
a better perspective well this is
literally dragging you down you keep
coming down because of that you lose
perspective so obviously if you
constantly live in the lower planes
you'll never get the perspective what if
you had if you lost it completely its
journey to retrace your steps and go
back up but what I'm saying is people
don't go back up to not go back to the
way why is the perspective because they
keep choosing sensuality choosing desire
choosing scratch and itch if you don't
choose it you would automatically
climbing up the hill on a higher ground
but this idea that by sort of teasing
those images learn to you know
challenging you're practicing with so
that's like like you're teasing a wild
crocodile yeah using a wild hyena that's
how you get stronger what's the result
of that you just gonna gonna basically
get you invoice when he gets you during
during the battle yeah you don't train a
dog by teasing it to be wild you train
it by calming it down so only person
basically you know who would say you
tease it the one that who couldn't calm
it down it was too weak to come an
animal down and then we try to make its
own way oh no no no no you're not
supposed to calm your senses down you
supposed to tease them out because
there's nothing else that I can gonna
Express run run with them run with them
yeah and run alongside the wild dog oh
why don't you try that
like actually get a wild dog because
then you tie yourself can tie yourself
to it and try running and see how far
you get if we under being dragged
against your will and if that's gonna be
that hard for a wild dog random wild
animal in
imagine how bad is going to be if you do
that to your own senses and also it's
based on presumption that you can run
what if you can't run anymore what if
and that's exactly the thing you know
where people depend on constantly having
something to do activity engagement
projects give meaning to the life
basically helps the float and if they
are left alone even for half a day
without company without engagement
without talking they start losing their
mind oh now there is nothing to run
along with to keep you occupied you are
left with the nature of that thing and
you realize oh my goodness this is
terrifying because it can we can rip
your part one animal runs to the left
the other animal runs to the right which
one do you want to follow because you
have six animals by the way six senses
so which one do you run with all six of
them how's that possible you want to
live with the wild animals oh you want
to live with the wild animals and at the
same time pretend they are not wild like
close yourself in the room with a
crocodile hyena wild macaques or any
chimp chimpanzee or something
and see how well that will go see a
piece for it how peaceful that will be
here no that's why it's not optional
calming your senses restraining your
senses it's not like oh I could do away
with this because I got this magic magic
technique for my meditation no there's
no meditation with our sensory strength
so you're gonna start meditation you
start sensitive strain that is your
meditation meditation will come out of
it once the animals come like these ones
and sit next to you because you're in
charge of them they are not in charge of
you and that's your own senses no I will
not look at that no I will not say that
no I will not go after that sense of
touch it's unpleasant yes so I choose
this discomfort when I count of far
worse discomfort but for a rabid mind
being dragged left and right by those
same senses okay you were trying to
appease because it's good it's good
for me Scripture exactly either way you
want to do what's good for you it's just
one person X I don't know but no real
perspective on what's really good for
you and another person develops
perspective what's really good for me
you do is actually feeding the wild
animal when it's in its fifth of madness
it's not good for me initially it calms
it down for a second but makes it in
water because I associates that wild
behavior with reward so I don't reward
the bog behavior i reward peaceful
behavior and that's hot that's hard to
train yourself well it's that basically
recognition I mean I we're still talking
about the simile or about it yourself
yes right well no it's like reward in
your own case say in terms of the sense
restraint the reward is absence of desire now
the reward is absence of desire now
because you keep increasing the desire
in the same sense you would increase the
madness of an animal by scratching it by
teasing it by feeding it by giving it
more when he wants more so initially it
hurts to say no but after a while desire
disappears could you stop scratching
your if you stopped it like freeing
yourself from addiction you wouldn't be
going back to that which you were
addicted when you free from addiction
but is no desire towards it and then you
recognize that whole relief who I'm free
from that big pressure of that desire
because I undo it away from it and then
you you won't go back to it I mean you
will if you completely lose wisdom again
if you completely lose perspective if
you completely stop recognizing that
that's much better for you and and much
more pleasurable actually yeah not to
not engage in that wild mad addiction
whatever else craving desire
satisfaction and so the absence of that
pressure
no does it it's Pleasant the pleasant
the absent of that pressure is the only
reason you give in to the pressure
because you want it to go away you don't
want and now you find a direct way that
doesn't involve giving in that doesn't
involve being dragged around by a wild
animal you found a direct way of removing the
you found a direct way of removing the
pressure basically deflating it deep
pressuring it renunciation and that's
the pleasure enunciation that's loftier
than any other pleasure you can
experience in this life can you have too
much of that no because that pleasure is
the Buddha said pleasure jhana base
let's talk about pronunciation which is
the pleasures of Jannah you can't
there is no craving for it it's the
result of you saying no to your craving
sufficiently long enough so then in the
Buddha realize he asked himself who is
this why am I afraid of displeasure
should I be afraid of this pleasures no
there is nothing unwholesome underlying
this pleasure
thus I won't be afraid of it now
cultivate because if you cut the eight
pairs of renunciation
at the same time you cannot cultivate
pleasure toward sensuality if you
calculate pain of renunciation pain of
elements pain of withdrawal you cannot
have the pain of household life pain of
losing your children pain of using the
well pain the flood like whatever abuse
anything else that people can suffer on
Carla if you want apply to you because
the mind is already far far be drawn
from that domain